Guillem Martí-Devesa CV

Astroparticle Physicist

Current Position: Research Grant at Universitá di Trieste & INFN

Fields: Astroparticle Physics, Gamma-Ray Astronomy

Coding: Python, C, Fortran, R, Java

Languages: Catalan, Spanish, English (professional), German (basic)

Tools: Fermitools, XSPEC, git, Tempo2, LATEX

Via Alfonso Valerio 2
Trieste, Italy
Dipartimento di Fisica
quillem.marti-devesa@ts.infn.it

Summary

Astroparticle physicist, member of the *Fermi* Large Area Telescope (*Fermi* LAT) and the High Energy Stereoscopic System (H. E. S. S.) Collaborations.

Expertise on Galactic Astroparticle Physics, particularly in stellar systems – binaries and stellar clusters – using multi-wavelength data (optical, X-ray, and γ ray). Main methods employed: Maximum-Likelihood Estimation and Time-Series Analysis.

Education

PhD in Physics - Universität Innsbruck, Austria

2017 - 2020

- · Thesis: Observational Studies on the Population of Binaries in the Gamma-Ray Sky
- · Doctoral schools at DIAS-DCU (Ireland), LAPP-CNRS (France) and ECAP-FAU (Germany). Radio analysis workshops by JIVE (Netherlands) and UK ARC-UM (United Kingdom)

MSc in Astro-, Particle Physics and Cosmology - Universitat de Barcelona, Spain

2016 - 2017

- · Thesis: First Multi-Filter Photometric Monitoring of the Be-BH System MWC 656
- · Courses on Statistics and Programming at ICCUB

BSc in Physics - Universitat de Barcelona, Spain

2012 - 2016

- · Thesis: Light Pollution in Barcelona: Night Sky Background Analysis
- · Observations performed at COU (Lleida, Spain) and Calar Alto (Almería, Spain)

Professional Degree in Music - Conservatori de Música de Barcelona, Spain

2008 - 2014

- · Honour Commendations in Chamber Music (2014) and Viola (2014)
- · Concerts performed in Spain (Barcelona, Valencia, Pamplona, and others), Austria (Innsbruck), France (Toulouse), Germany (Steingaden), and Italy (Dobbiaco) with multiple semi-professional and amateur orchestras.

Work Experience

General - Professional Service

- · Member of the Fermi-LAT and H.E.S.S. collaborations since 2018
- · Fermi-LAT's Galactic Science Group co-coordinator since September 2022
- · Journal referee for AJ, ApJ, and A&A

Research Grant - Università di Trieste & INFN, Italy

2024 - Now

- · Studies on Galactic and Extragalactic γ -ray sources
- · Development of new analysis methods for Fermi-LAT

Universitätsassistent – Postdoc - Universität Innsbruck, Austria

2020 - 2023

- · Studies on Galactic γ -ray sources
- · Teaching between 4 and 6 hours weekly every semester

- \cdot Studies on γ -ray binary systems
- · One-month shift at H.E.S.S. site (Namibia), and remote data quality monitoring shifts with H.E.S.S. and Fermi-LAT

Research assistant - Institut d'Estudis Espacials de Catalunya, Spain

2015 - 2017

MSc - Summer 2023

- · Studies on light pollution in natural reserves
- · Participation in the LoNNe calibration campaign in 2016 at COU observatory

Teaching

PR: Practical training course; PS: Exercise course; SE: Seminar; VO: Lecture; VU: Lecture-exercise course

| At Universität Innsbruck | 2021 - 2023 |
|---|-----------------------------|
| · PR Programming for Physics Students | BSc - Summer 2021 & 22 & 23 |
| · PS Physics IV: Nuclear and Particle Physics | BSc - Summer 2021 & 22 |
| · VU Astroparticle Physics I | MSc - Fall 2021/22 |
| · PR Laboratory for Computational Physics A | MSc - Fall 2021/22 & 21/22 |
| · VU Binary Systems in Astrophysics (new creation) | MSc - Fall 2021/22 |
| · PS Physics I: Mechanics and Thermodynamics | BSc - Fall 2022/23 |
| · VO Introduction to Astroparticle Physics | BSc - Fall 2022/23 |
| · SE Bachelor Thesis Seminar (Astroparticle and Particle Physics coordinator) | BSc - 2023 |
| · VU Astroparticle Physics II | MSc - Summer 2023 |

Supervision

Bachelor Theses

· VU Theoretical Astrophysics

| · High-Energy Gamma-Rays from the Omega Nebula – Daniel Resch | Summer 2021 |
|--|-------------|
| · Gamma-Ray Flares of the Microquasar Cygnus X-3: a Fermi-LAT Perspective – Mike Wettke | Summer 2022 |
| · Understanding the High-Energy Emission from the Omega Nebula – Sandrino Achenreiner | Summer 2022 |
| · The Crab Nebula seen by H.E.S.S. and Fermi-LAT with Open-Source Tools – Melanie Federer† | Summer 2023 |
| · The PWN MHS 15-52 as seen with H.E.S.S. and Fermi-LAT — Lukas Sabathil [†] | Summer 2023 |
| · Neutrinos from Colliding Stellar Winds – Bernhard Lang | Summer 2023 |
| · Anisotropic Inverse Compton from Cygnus X-1 – Philipp Aichner | Summer 2023 |
| Master Theses | |
| · Star Forming Regions as Hadronic Cosmic-Ray Accelerators – Nadine Bourriche* | 2021 - 2022 |

[†] Co-supervised with Dr. Markus Holler

Other

· Mentor within the Fermi LAT Mentoring Program

Since 2022

Granted observing time

Proposals

| · VLA (PI: Marcote): CEN 1a and 1b: The third case of a colliding wind binary emitting gamma rays? | 2023 |
|---|---------|
| · EVN+e-Merlin (PI: Marcote): CEN 1a and 1b: The third case of a colliding-wind binary emitting gamma rays? | 2023 |
| NICER Cycle 5 (PI: Marti-Devesa): Wind-wind interaction and particle acceleration in the Kleinmann Star trapezium system. Additional NuSTAR time. | 2023 |
| · H.E.S.S. internal proposals (PI or co-author, information not public) | 2020/24 |

^{*} Co-supervised with Prof. Olaf Reimer

Talks

Conferences

| · TAUP 2023, Vienna, Austria | August 2023 |
|--|----------------|
| · VGGRS Workshop VI, Innsbruck, Austria (invited talk & LOC) | April 2023 |
| Cosmic Magnetism in Voids and Filaments, Bologna, Italy | January 2023 |
| · Gamma 2022, Barcelona, Spain | July 2022 |
| · 9th Fermi Symposium, Johannesburg, South Africa (Virtual) | April 2021 |
| · VGGRS Workshop V, Barcelona, Spain | September 2019 |

Invited seminars

| · ICCUB Seminar, Barcelona, Spain | September 2022 |
|--|----------------|
| · MPIK's Astrophysics Seminar, Heidelberg, Germany (Virtual) | July 2021 |

Outreach

Activities

· Cloud chamber experiment and Sun observations with high-school students

ICCUB - Jan 2017

Talks

· Understanding the Universe: Astroparticle Physics in Tirol

Mittelschule 2 Wörgl – Oct 2022

Publications

Main journal publications

- [1] **G. Martí-Devesa*** et al. "Early-time γ -ray constraints on cosmic-ray acceleration in the core-collapse SN 2023ixf with the Fermi Large Area Telescope". In: A&A accepted; NASA press release (Apr. 2024).
- [2] P. Da Vela*, **G. Martí-Devesa**, F. G. Saturni, P. Veres, A. Stamerra and F. Longo. "Intergalactic magnetic field studies by means of γ -ray emission from GRB 190114C". In: *PRD* 107, 6 (Mar. 2023), p. 063030. DOI: 10.1103/PhysRevD.107.063030. arXiv: 2303.03137 [astro-ph.HE].
- [3] **G. Martí-Devesa***, O. Reimer, and A. Reimer. "Limits on the non-thermal emission of the WR-WR system Apep". In: *A&A* 670, L6 (Feb. 2023), p. L6. DOI: 10.1051/0004-6361/202245332. arXiv: 2212.10146 [astro-ph.HE].
- [4] C. C. Cheung*, T. J. Johnson*, P. Jean*, M. Kerr, K. L. Page, J. P. Osborne, A. P. Beardmore, K. V. Sokolovsky, F. Teyssier, S. Ciprini, **G. Martí-Devesa**, I. Mereu, S. Razzaque, K. S. Wood, S. N. Shore, S. Korotkiy, A. Levina and A. Blumenzweig. "Fermi LAT Gamma-ray Detection of the Recurrent Nova RS Ophiuchi during its 2021 Outburst". In: *ApJ* 935.1, 44 (Aug. 2022), p. 44. DOI: 10.3847/1538-4357/ac7eb7. arXiv: 2207.02921 [astro-ph.HE].
- [5] **G. Martí-Devesa*** and O. Reimer. " η Carinae with Fermi-LAT: two full orbits and the third periastron". In: A&A 654, A44 (Oct. 2021), A44. DOI: 10.1051/0004-6361/202140451. arXiv: 2109.05950 [astro-ph.HE].
- [6] **G. Martí-Devesa*** and O. Reimer. "X-ray and γ -ray orbital variability from the γ -ray binary HESS J1832-093". In: A&A 637, A23 (May 2020), A23. DOI: 10.1051/0004-6361/202037442. arXiv: 2001.02701 [astro-ph.HE].
- [7] **G. Martí-Devesa***, O. Reimer, J. Li and D. F. Torres. "Hints of γ -ray orbital variability from γ^2 Velorum". In: A&A 635, A141 (Mar. 2020), A141. DOI: 10.1051/0004-6361/202037462. arXiv: 2001.02708 [astro-ph.HE].

Reports in The Astronomer's Telegram

- [8] C. C. Cheung*, T. J. Johnson, P. Jean, and **G. Marti-Devesa**. "Fermi-LAT daily aperture light curve of T CrB now available". In: *The Astronomer's Telegram* 16336 (Nov. 2023), p. 1.
- [9] **G. Martí-Devesa***. "Fermi-LAT gamma-ray observations of SN 2023ixf". In: *The Astronomer's Telegram* 16075 (June 2023), p. 1.
- [10] **G. Martí-Devesa***. "Fermi-LAT detection of enhanced gamma-ray activity from the FSRQ PKS 0700-465". In: *The Astronomer's Telegram* 16048 (May 2023), p. 1.
- [11] T. J. Johnson, **G. Martí-Devesa**, and C.C. Cheung*. "Detection of enhanced emission above 100 MeV, using Fermi-LAT data, associated with the PSR B1259-63/LS 2883 binary system approximately 60 days after periastron". In: *The Astronomer's Telegram* 14540 (Apr. 2021), p. 1.